<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.soyeb_jim285.HyprFM</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>

  <name>HyprFM</name>
  <summary>Lightweight Qt6/QML file manager for Hyprland</summary>

  <description>
    <p>
      HyprFM is a fast, keyboard-driven file manager built with Qt6 and QML.
      It is designed for tiling Wayland compositors like Hyprland but works on
      any Wayland desktop session.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Grid, detailed and Miller column views with image and video thumbnails</li>
      <li>Full-screen quick preview overlay for images, video, PDFs, audio and text</li>
      <li>Tabs with per-tab history and a split pane view for working in two locations at once</li>
      <li>Keyboard-first navigation with vim-friendly bindings, type-ahead jump and customizable shortcuts</li>
      <li>fd-powered search with glob and full-path matching</li>
      <li>Async copy and move via rsync with live progress, speed, ETA and pause/resume</li>
      <li>Bulk rename with regular expressions, drag and drop, undo and redo</li>
      <li>XDG-compliant trash with restore, archive compress and extract, Open With dialog</li>
      <li>Removable device mounting via UDisks2 and remote filesystem browsing (sftp, smb, dav) via gvfs</li>
      <li>Git status overlays for modified, staged, untracked and conflicted files</li>
      <li>TOML themes with live reload, configurable corner radius, fonts and animations</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.soyeb_jim285.HyprFM.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm</url>

  <developer id="io.github.soyeb_jim285">
    <name>Soyeb Pervez Jim</name>
  </developer>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Grid view with file preview</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm/v0.4.7/docs/screenshots/grid-view.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Miller column view</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm/v0.4.7/docs/screenshots/miller-view.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Quick preview overlay</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/soyeb-jim285/hyprfm/v0.4.7/docs/screenshots/quick-preview.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>FileManager</category>
  </categories>

  <provides>
    <binary>hyprfm</binary>
  </provides>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.4.8" date="2026-04-08">
      <description>
        <p>Fix the AppImage on Wayland sessions: build QtWayland from source in CI so the wayland-graphics-integration-client plugins (which aqtinstall's base Qt omits) are present for linuxdeploy to bundle. Without this, Qt aborted on startup with "Available client buffer integrations: QList()".</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.7" date="2026-04-08">
      <description>
        <p>Flathub submission polish: install the license file at the Flatpak-standard location, pin bundled git sources to immutable commit SHAs, drop unused DBus name claims and redundant filesystem permissions, and reference screenshots by tag instead of branch.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.6" date="2026-04-08">
      <description>
        <p>Documentation polish: correct the feature list in the AppStream metadata to match the three views HyprFM actually ships (grid, detailed and Miller columns) and expand it to mention git status overlays, remote access, quick preview and archive support.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.5" date="2026-04-08">
      <description>
        <p>Major release adding Flatpak support and reworking several backend pieces for sandbox compatibility.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New Flathub-ready Flatpak build targeting the KDE 6.9 runtime.</li>
          <li>Mount and unmount now talk to UDisks2 directly over DBus (no udisksctl dependency), which also makes the feature work inside sandboxes.</li>
          <li>File icons and thumbnail classification now use the system MIME database, so ambiguous extensions like .ts (TypeScript vs MPEG-TS) and modern image formats like AVIF/HEIC are recognized correctly.</li>
          <li>Open With, trash operations, and opening files in host apps all work correctly inside a Flatpak by routing through flatpak-spawn --host.</li>
          <li>Sidebar fill bar for the root partition now reports the real host usage inside a Flatpak.</li>
          <li>Recents, Search and Trash views no longer fail to render delegates when the model lacks git status roles.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.4" date="2026-04-07">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle the Qt Wayland platform plugin in the AppImage and add qt6-wayland as an explicit dependency in the .deb so the window renders correctly on Ubuntu's GNOME Wayland session.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.3" date="2026-04-07">
      <description>
        <p>Detect the fdfind binary on Debian/Ubuntu (where the fd-find package ships fd as fdfind to avoid a name clash).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.2" date="2026-04-06">
      <description>
        <p>Initial Flathub-targeted release.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
